<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The three kingdomes case: or, Their sad calamities, together with their causes and cure. Laid down in a sermon preached at a publique fast at Kingston upon Hull. With some very remarkable passages of providence worthy of generall observation. /</title>
            <author>Shawe, John, 1608-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3030</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E330_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200707</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861378</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861378</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113511</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113511)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 54:E330[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The three kingdomes case: or, Their sad calamities, together with their causes and cure. Laid down in a sermon preached at a publique fast at Kingston upon Hull. With some very remarkable passages of providence worthy of generall observation. /</title>
                  <author>Shawe, John, 1608-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 23, 26-29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.B. for John Bartlet, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the gilt Cup, under Saint Austins Gate.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text is continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah XLII, 24-25 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113511:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113511:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The three Kingdomes Caſe: OR, Their ſad Calamities, together with Their CAVSES and CVRE. Laid down in a SERMON PREACHED AT A Publique Faſt at <hi>Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Hull.</hi> With ſome very remarkable Paſſages of Providence worthy of generall Obſervation.</p>
            <p>By JOHN SHAWE <hi>M. A.</hi> ſometimes of <hi>Christs</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge:</hi> and now Lecturer at <hi>Hull</hi> aforeſaid.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JER. 12. 10, 11, 12. </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>They have made my pleaſant portion a deſolate wilderneſſe—being deſolate it mourneth unto me, the whole land is made deſolate, becauſe no man layeth it to heart: the ſpoylers are come upon all high places through the wilderneſſe, for the ſword of the Lord ſhall devoure from one end of the land even to the other, &amp;c. no fleſh ſhall have peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nullus ferè credit quod propter peccata noſtra variis modus Deus animadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat in homines hujus ſecule: maior pars ſecurè praeterit quaecun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> profert Deus irae ſuae iudicia, alii fortunae tribuunt quae videntur in orbe converſiones ac mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes: in ſummâ pauci ſunt vel propemodum nulli qui manifesta dei iudicia expendant,</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Aug.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plectimur à Deo, nec flectimur tamen; corripimur, ſed non corrigimur,</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>Salv.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. B.</hi> for <hi>John Bartlet,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the Signe of the gilt Cup, under Saint <hi>Austins</hi> Gate. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113511:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113511:2"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian and wel-affected READER, eſpecially to my worthy and loving friends, both the Inhabitants within the Town and Country of <hi>Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Hull,</hi> and alſo the Pariſhoners of <hi>Bradfield,</hi> in the Weſt-riding of <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire:</hi> Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Readers and friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Have looked with <hi>Elijah's</hi> ſervant more then ſeven times, to ſee what would be the iſſue of theſe troubles, <hi>1 Kin. 18. 43.</hi> and I long ſince espied a great cloud (bigger then his, ver. 44. yea, like that ver. 45) and trembled becauſe of this matter, and for the great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ez. 10. 9. &amp;</hi> my ſelf have felt neither few nor ſmall drops of theſe troubles (as you know;) and truly ſtil, if I did not ſee that the great and wiſe God had a ſpeciall hand in carrying on, and ordering al theſe wars and combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, I yet ſee ſo much malice, private ſpleen even in thoſe who return home and ſit ſtill, ſuch factions, ſciſms, and upon (any occaſion) apoſtacies; in a word, ſo much of that many-headed Monſter <hi>Selfe,</hi> yet in the Kingdomes, that I could hardly expect fair, quiet, ſun-ſhine dayes of long, but that the Lord raigneth, and therefore may the earth rejoyce, and this poor Iſland be glad thereof, <hi>Pſal. 97. 1.</hi> I have in the enſuing lines, opened and applied, as I could, what the word and ſword, my Text and times hold out unto you. My Text tels of war, plunderings, ſpoilings, which <note n="a" place="margin">In locum.</note> 
               <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom</hi> refers to the overthrow of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> after Chriſt, by <hi>Titus,</hi> becauſe the Jewes rejected Chriſt, the Son of God, and ſalvation by him, <hi>(oſtendens ferociam Romanorum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in populum Judaeorum qui idcirco punitus
<pb facs="tcp:113511:3"/> eſt quia Dei filium non recepit.) Piſcator</hi> refers to the troubles of the Jewes by <hi>Zenacherib</hi> and the <hi>Aſſyrians, Calvin</hi> to the plague, famine, wars and all ſuch miſeries laid on them by the Lord at ſeverall times; others, to <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzars</hi> deſolating wars, and the Jewes ſeventy yeers captivity; <hi>Muſculus</hi> to the war and miſery which Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael endured by the <hi>Philiſtines, Idumaeans, Amorites, Moabites, Syrians, Aſſyrians, &amp;c.</hi> notwithstanding all which troubles, Iſrael could not be perſwaded that ſin was the cauſe, but either chance, or becauſe they wanted their number of men, and were not ſtrong enough; but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet propheſieth ſin to be the true cauſe, and confeſſeth, that he living among them, had contracted ſinne and guilt, ſo as that he had a hand in bringing downe theſe Judgements, <hi>(we have ſinned)</hi> yet preſently in the ſame verſe, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the perſon, his ſin not being ſo wilfull, contemptuous, and perſerved in as theirs, ver. 24. <hi>(they would not walk)</hi> yet in theſe ſad wars and combuſtions of ours in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (like thoſe in the Text) I ſee ſome grounds of hope; as firſt, a budding generation comming up, hungring and gasping after Chriſt and the means of grace (a good ſigne that God is not leaving our land, but that the time of the promiſe drawes nigh, <hi>Acts 7. 17. Iſa. 49. 20, 21.)</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, many active and eminent spirits raiſed up like <hi>Moſes, Aaron. Phineas,</hi> like <hi>Zerubbabel</hi> and <hi>Joſhua,</hi> for the work of the Lord in Church and State with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, <hi>Hag. 1. 12, 14. Jer. 50. 2. Micah 5. 5.</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, cleerer light ſhines in the Kingdom (even by contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which ſatan ſtirs up to overthrow the truth) and in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dark corners, <hi>Dan. 12, 4.</hi> adde to theſe, that the iron and clay break aſunder daily, <hi>Dan. 2. 41, 42.</hi> and the ſtone cut out without hands growes more and more, <hi>Dan. 2. 43, 44, 45.</hi> and I ſee all this carried on above, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb facs="tcp:113511:3"/> to the power and policy of the ſubtilleſt heads, by the mervailous hand of God, <hi>Zach. 4. 6.</hi> let me to the only praiſe of the wonder-working God, and the better to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate the memories of his miracles of mercies to this Town of <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Hull</hi> (which place, if ever any is moſt infinitely indebted to God, who hath ſhewed mercies indeed to other places, but to this town miracles) let me (I ſay) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſome particular mercies which God hath afforded to this town, wherein it appears, that God himſelf hath bared his arme and ſaved it beyond, and contrary to the wit and will of the ſubtilleſt enemies and ſeeming friends, and made the very enemies to help on your ſafety, and their owne ruine; as appears, firſt, in that a little before theſe wars began, your Castle and block-houſes were out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, and too much (through long peace and diſ-uſe) unfit for ſervice; upon which pretence, ſome of the Kings Coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men begged them of the King, and ſued you for them; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon you preſently repaired them; which Forts, thus on this occaſion repaired, helped now to keep out the Kings party: Secondly, whereas formerly you had no draw-bridges to keep out an enemy, Captain <hi>W. Legge</hi> and others of that party cauſed draw-bridges to be made about the Town, on purpoſe to keep out our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> when firſt they came into this land for our aſſiſtance; but theſe bridges kept out Captain <hi>Leg</hi> and that party: Thirdly, Arms were alſo ſent hither for above 20000. men, under the manag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſaid Cap. <hi>Leg;</hi> &amp; after that, a Garriſonof 1000. ſhould. here planted (having not bin any here for many yeers before) under the command of Sir <hi>Tho. Glenham,</hi> by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection &amp; advice of the Earl of <hi>Strafford</hi> (for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe aforeſaid) and yet all this turned to keep out that very party: Fourthly, in the dawning of theſe troubles, Captain <hi>Leg</hi> being ſetled in this Town, and having this ſtrength and power aforeſaid, and the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> being alſo
<pb facs="tcp:113511:4"/> ſent hither by the King, with his Commiſſion to be Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour here (who came into the Town by the name of Sir <hi>John Savage)</hi> but the town demurred upon their anſwer to him, till they heard from the Parliament) both theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (viz. Earl and Captain) thus in the town, upon a bare ſummons from Parliament, left the Town and posted to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (a thing which I beleeve both of them have forethought an hundred times ſince.) Fifthly, the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King came firſt to <hi>Hull,</hi> to demand or command entrance (Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> being then Governour here) the King ſent the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> the Prince Elector, the Earl of <hi>Newport,</hi> the Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Glenham,</hi> and others, into <hi>Hull,</hi> which cauſed ſome jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies in the Governour and Townſ-men, whereas if the King had come ſuddenly to the gates, without any warning, when the Duke and the reſt came, I am confident none had then ſuspected his comming, nor would any ſouldier have hindred his entry at the gates (ſuch a work was then rare.) Sixthly, the next day after (viz. about Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 25. 1642. being ſaturday) the King with ſome hundreds of atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, came to enter the Town of <hi>Hull</hi> (the Governour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing buſied in entertaining the Duke of <hi>York,</hi> the Prince Elector, and their Company) and had the King ſtill come without any further warning, ſuddenly to the gates, I am confident no ſouldier would have hindred him; but the King ſent Sir <hi>Lewes Dives</hi> two hours before him, to tell the Governour that the King was within four or five miles off, and would dine with him (and this time and warning had Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> to adviſe and hearten himſelf and his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, to keep out that company that came with the King, and to draw up their bridges, &amp;c. Seventhly, adde this for a wonder, that Sir <hi>John Hotham</hi> ſhould then ſo reſolutely keep theſe perſons out, having ſuch a numerous party of the
<pb facs="tcp:113511:4"/> contrary mind, moſt active that day; both within and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out againſt him (a work at that time not for every mans ſpirit) himſelf, as ſince it appears, proving ſo unfaithfull; of whom and which work, I may this ſay, that when he could have ruined the Town, and endangered the Kingdom there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, he would not, and after when he would have done it, he could not: Eighthly, when the Kings Army came firſt againſt this Towne, they (thinking thereby to have compelled you to yeeld) burnt your Mils, but this did wonderfully ſet the hearts of all, both rich and poor againſt them (their food being endangered) whereas ſome of them before were not ſo fully affected to the Parliament and that cauſe. Ninthly, the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> after this, having over-mastred all the North, ſave <hi>Hull</hi> and <hi>Wreſle Caſtle,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving got ſo great and formidable an Army, with which he might in probability have gone through moſt parts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> then, and have ruined or endangered many a City, Town and County, yet were his old, wiſeſt and ſubtilleſt ſouldiers ſo far befooled, that they perſwaded him to bring this Army againſt <hi>Hull, in Auguſt 1643.</hi> and lay a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſiege here; but partly by the ſhot and ſallies out of the Town, partly by lying in wet trenches (the Country round about being drowned at spring-tides) their whole Army was brought almoſt to nothing, and thoſe that were left of them (now no way formidabe) after ſix weeks and odde dayes ſiege, went away with infinite ſhame and loſſe, <hi>October 11. 1643.</hi> (for which mercy you ſtill keep on that day an aniverſary thankfull commemoration.)</p>
            <p>Tenthly, In all theſe ſix weeks ſiege, though the enemy ſhot many fiery hot bullets into the Town night and day, yet very few of you were hurt; ſometimes many wel-affected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were met in a chamber to repeat ſermons, and pray, as ſoon as ever they were departed and gone down the ſtairs,
<pb facs="tcp:113511:5"/> (and not till then) came a red hot bullet through the place where they met; ſo in another chamber where children went to ſchool, came another of thoſe fiery meſſengers as ſoon as ever the children were gone from that place, and none hurt.</p>
            <p>Eleventhly, on Thurſday, <hi>June 29. 1643.</hi> when <hi>Sir John Hotham</hi> was conceived trecherous, he being alwayes very active and vigilant, and especially then, yet were the Magazine, the ſeverall guards and forts of the garriſon ſeized on by the Townſ-men and others (no experienced ſouldiers) within the compaſſe of leſſe then an hour (and that before <hi>Sir John Hotham</hi> was aware) without the loſſe of any blood (which great and hazardous attempt, one would have thought, and it was feared, would have coſt many a mans life.</p>
            <p>Twelfthly, that on the very day after this (viz. Friday, <hi>June 30. 1643.)</hi> the right Honourable and Noble Lord General <hi>Fairfax</hi> had that great loſſe at <hi>Atherton More,</hi> and when he was retired from the field into <hi>Leeds,</hi> and was in danger, yet more ſad and troubled (as his Lordſhip ſaid) for the loſſe of his men and the danger of the Country (and not well knowing which way, or what courſe to take the next day) a Boy came juſt in that nick <note n="b" place="margin">Like the <hi>caſe of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai,</hi> or the <hi>Shunamite, Eſt.</hi> 5. 14. with 6. 1, 4, 6, 10. 2 King. 8. 5.</note> of time, with a Letter from the Major and Aldermen of <hi>Hull,</hi> acquaitnting his Honour, that <hi>Hull</hi> was open for him if he would come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that the town and ammunition were ſeized upon, as aforeſaid; <hi>Sir Iohn Horham</hi> fled, and in his flight ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in <hi>Beverley,</hi> (a joyfull meſſage at that time, though till then, neither had his honour heard thereof, nor the town, when they ſent, of Lordſhips loſſe.)</p>
            <p>13. Though it was generally ſaid and thought, that if the wars ſhould continue, and Armies ſhould lye <hi>in York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> but one yeer, there could not poſſibly be any proviſion
<pb facs="tcp:113511:5"/> or food left; yet have Armies been here almoſt ſix yeers already, in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> ſometimes ſix Generals and their Armies at once, often above 20000<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. ſouldiers abominable firing, ſpoiling, plundering, &amp;c. yet ſeldom have we ſeen meat &amp; drink more cheap or plentifull here, then ſtill it is (bleſſed be God:) This is the Lords own doing; thus have you Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, ſeen Gods wonders as much by Land
<note n="c" place="margin">Pſa. 107. 23 24.</note> as by Sea, and this Town ſometimes a poor Hamlet called <hi>Wyke,</hi> after, in <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond his time, called the Kings Towne (upon the River <hi>Hull)</hi> which is a greater honour, then if by the cowardize or trechery of any, it had been turned to be (in that ſenſe that ſome badly mean it) the Queens Town, may now justly be called Gods Town, becauſe of the miracles God hath wrought for it. (Oh that it appeared to be ſo by our holy practice anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">Pſal. 116, 12, 13.</note> to ſuch mervailous mercies!)</p>
            <p>To conclude, let me for the ſame end acquaint you, the Inhabitants of <hi>Bradfield,</hi> with another instance, though of a lower ranke, <hi>viz.</hi> the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailous delivery of a Minister of Christs Goſpel, born in your Pariſh, wherein you may ſtill ſee Gods hand; learn to truſt and praiſe him more: 'tis this, When the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi> beſieged <hi>Rotherham in May 1643.</hi> at laſt, the Towne wanting powder (which was taken at <hi>Gainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough,</hi> as it was bringing to them) and ſome bouſes being on fire by the enemies Granadoes, the Town was forced to entertaine a parley with the Earl, who after ſome ſhamefull repulſe and loſſe) aſſured them under his hand, that upon laying down their Arms, they ſhould have their estates, lives and liberties ſafe; but as ſoon as be entred, fined, impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned, plundered many, and as it ſeems had a ſpeciall intent to ruine the Minister of that place aforeſaid; yet, firſt, that Minister went through the midſt of the Town (then ſo throng'd) undiſcerned by any; ſecondly, he hid himſelf in a vault of a bouſe not inhabited (after he heard of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies baſe unfaithfulneſſe and cruelty) which houſe (the enemy pulling downe the Works about the Towne) came into, and kept as their main guard night and day, and lay cloſe by him (which thing he neither did nor could ſuſpect before-band;) thirdly, the enemy proclaimed him traitor by a cryer throughout the Town, yea, and all others traitors alſo, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, brought him not in to them within 24. hours; in the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid bouſe the ſouldiers ſeeking him moſt diligently, thruſt their ſwords betwixt the Loards frequently, yet neither found, nor hurt him; fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, at laſt they looked up to a vault above their heads (which lay viſibly open to view, by the ſpace of three yards and more, where himſelf and his man lay indeed) and ſwore that he was there, whereupon they instantly ran up their ſtairs (which they kept) broke open the door (entring to the vault
<pb facs="tcp:113511:6"/> which they ſaw, and where he was) found it lockt, and the key in the door on the in-ſide, ſought him five ſeverall times, the great windowes all open round about, be and his man lying on their ſides, could have taken hold on them, yet never found either of them (no cauſe but that <hi>Jer.</hi> 36. 26) fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he having layen there on the ſtones moſt part of three days and nights, <hi>viz.</hi> from Thurſday May 4. 1643. (when the Town was taken) till Saturday evening May 6. could not ſtir, ſcarce cough or ſpet, left be ſhould be heard, and no friend, meat, drink or relief could come at him (the enemy keeping the Town, that houſe and ſtairs to the vault) be reſolved that night, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then ſtarve, to goe down and yeeld himſelf to their cruell mercies (for be might hear them ſwear his death with many dammees) preſently, that very afternoon they went away (be cannot to this day learn any reaſon why) for they came thither again the next day, and ſtaid there constantly long after, as if they had meant (as indeed the good and wiſe God did) to give him juſt a fit time and ſpace to get ſafe away, for neither before nor after could be get away thence, nor longer ſtay here: ſixthly, when he was come down the ſtairs from the vault, though the enemy be found removed, yet were the doors lock; but the enemy had cauſed a Carpenter to pull up two boards of the floor to ſeek for him in a hollow place underneath, and left them unnailed down again; through which ſpace (as if they had ment to have made him away forth) be got out: ſeventhly, when he came forth
<note place="margin">Acts 12. 7, 10.</note> by that hollow aforeſaid, he came through the midſt of the Town again to his houſe undiſcerned; and as he was ſtepping into the Hall (not knowing now who lived there or in any other houſe) there were ſeven Cavaliers billeted (having formerly plundered him ſufficiently) amongst whom he was juſt ſtepping, had not a friend of his pulled him by the ſhoulders into another Room next the Hall: eighthly, yet durſt he not carry there, but got to a vault in another houſe, and lay upon an earthern floor the remainder of three weeks in the midſt among them, yet never got cold, nor was the leaſt ſick, no not ſo much as uſually before: ninthly, after this he got ſafe to <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> &amp; after ſome cumbers, is ſafely returned to his nativeCoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; for all which, he entreats his friendly neighbours and readers that praiſes may be returned to the only wiſe God, and ſole and lively confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence put in him for ever and ever. Which paſſages (Christian Reader) together with the enſuing notes, bad I not been importuned to publiſh, till I was in <hi>Eliſhah's</hi> caſe, <hi>2 Kin. 2. 17.</hi> nor thou nor I had had this trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: however, if God may have glory, his Cauſe any furtherance, or any of his people profit by them, I have all my aime, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The unworthieſt of the leaſt of Gods mercies, J. S.</signed>
               <dateline>Hull
<date>Novemb. 17. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113511:6"/>
            <head>The three Kingdomes CASE, with their CAVSES and CVRE. OR, A SERMON Preached at <hi>Kingston</hi> upon H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LL.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ISA. 42. 24, 25.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>Who gave Iacob for a ſpoile and Iſrael to the Robbers? Did not the Lord, he againſt whom we have ſinned, for they would not walk in his wayes, neither were they obedient unto his Law?</p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Ver. </seg>25</label> Therefore he hath poured upon him the fury of his Anger, and the ſtrength of battell, and it hath ſet him on fire round about, yet he knew it not, and it burned him, yet he laid it not to heart.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Need not (right Honourable and beloved) to uſe any other motive to beſpeak your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions then the words immediately fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going my Text, verſe 23. <hi>Who among you will give eare unto this? who will hearken and beare for the time to come?</hi> Only give me leave for the cleering of the words, to acquaint you (and that very briefly) firſt, with the Prophet; ſecondly, the time when; thirdly, perſons to whom he propheſied; fourthly, the ſubſtance of his propheſie. Divines uſe to caſt the ſixteen Prophets (whoſe propheſies are recorded in the old
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113511:7"/> Teſtament) into three ranks; firſt, ſome propheſied before the Jewes ſeventy yeers captivity in <hi>Babilon,</hi> as <hi>Jonah, Hoſea, Iſaiah,</hi> and ſome others: Secondly, ſome of them gave cordials in the time of the captivity, as <hi>Ez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iel</hi> and <hi>Daniel:</hi> Thirdly, others quickned them after the captivity, and their returne, as <hi>Haggai, Zechariah, Malachi.</hi> Amongſt theſe, our Prophet is of the firſt ranke, yet though his propheſie be ranked in the firſt place, its not probable that he was the firſt of them in time that prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied, but rather <hi>Jonab,</hi> who propheſied before (or at leaſt in the beginning of) the raigne of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> the ſecond, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 14. 25 (whereas <hi>Hoſea,</hi> though you grant him to be a Preacher ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeers, began but in the latter end of his raigne, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1. 1.) ſo in the new Teſtament its thought by the Hiſtory in the Acts of the Apoſtles, that not the Epiſtle to the Romans (though placed the firſt) but that to the Theſſalonians was firſt writ; alſo, not the book of <hi>Malachi,</hi> but <hi>Nehemiah</hi> was the laſt book in order of time and ſtory in the old Teſtament.</p>
            <p>This Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was nobly borne, by both births, of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and grace, being of the royall blood both of Heaven and earth (let no man think himſelfe too good, by reaſon of his birth or eſtate, to be Gods Prophet, ſee <hi>David, Solomon, Iſaiah, &amp;c.</hi> God cals to this office, ſometimes men of greater birth and eſtates, as this <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſonne of <hi>Amoz,</hi> ſometimes poorer, as <hi>Amos,</hi> a poore Neat-heard of <hi>Tekoah, Amos</hi> 1. 1. which two names <note n="a" place="margin">Robuſtus fortis, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Onuſtus durus <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. in Iſa. 1.</note> differ much both in the Hebrew writing and ſignification) <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſied above ſixty yeers to a ſtubborne people of the Jewes, that profited little (ſo did <hi>Hoſea</hi> to Iſrael above ſeventy yeers) yet would not leave off his Miniſtry; to leave off ones Miniſtry becauſe he cannot ſee it doe that good which he wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth (ſaith old <hi>Latimer)</hi> is a naughty, a very naughty deed.</p>
            <p>After all his toile and paines, he was ſawne aſunder by his neere Kinſman; let us learne to be content, though ill reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by men, ſeeing this Evangelicall and noble Prophet was ſo uſed, after ſo long and great paines for their ſoules good.</p>
            <p>The ſumme of the Propheſie is a diſcovery of the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Jewes, and of Gods judgements againſt the impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent for thoſe finnes, together with a promiſe to the Elect, and propheſie of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; his birth, life, death, reſurrection, aſcenſion, and interceſſion.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113511:7"/>
            <p>In this chapter, the Lord holds out Chriſt full of beauty and bounty, goodneſſe and pitty, ver. 1. 10. exhorteth the Jewes to prize and praiſe him, ver. 10. 13. but foreſeeing their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and rejecting of ſuch an invaluable mercy, he denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth heavy judgements againſt them, ver. 13. to the end, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of my Text is part. In which, conſider, firſt, the puniſher, the Lord; ſecondly, the puniſhment, battell, war, with the fruits of it, robbing, firing, ſpoyling, &amp;c. And thirdly, the puniſhed, not Heathens, but the Members of Gods viſible Church, <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob, Iſrael;</hi> fourthly, the meritorious cauſe of this puniſhment, ſinne and diſobedience, neglecting Gods wayes; fifthly, the Peoples incorrigibleneſſe and unprofitableneſſe under all this, they conſider not, nor lay it to heart. I will graſpe as much together as I can, and collect ſome obſervations as ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Text, occaſion and time, as with conveniency I may. And firſt this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 1. That warre with the fruits thereof, robbing, firing, ſpoyling, are very ſad and heavy calamities, yet ſuch as may befall a Nation profeſſing the true Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 2. That when ſuch warres befall ſuch a Nation, it's God that ſends them, and gives up a people to them <hi>(Who gave Iſrael to the robbers, did not the Lord?)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 3. When ever God ſends ſuch warres and calamities on ſuch a Nation, their ſinnes and iniquities were the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing and meritorious cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 4. That when a people have ſuch judgements pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon them by God, and yet doe not conſider rightly thereof, and lay it to heart, it much provokes and angers God.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, that the ſtrength of battell, robbing, firing and ſpoyling, are ſad calamities, it needs no further proofe, it's too apparent already; I may ſay of this, as our Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 4. 21. this day is this Scripture fulfilled in your eares; yet that this point may prove more uſefull to us, let me a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle cut it up, and ſhew you the miſeries of warre; firſt, by the precedents or occaſions of it; ſecondly, the nature of it; third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the conſequents, eſpecially of a civill warre (ſuch as ours now is.)</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113511:8"/>
            <p>And firſt, for the occaſions of warre, I will name ſome; as it's a ſad thing when King a and people fall out, and claſh one with another till one weaken another, and endanger the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of both; thus <hi>Abimilech</hi> and the men of <hi>Sechem,</hi> the Lord ſent an evill ſpirit of diſſention betwixt them, <hi>Judg.</hi> 9. 22, 23. after <hi>Abimilech</hi> had raigned a while, ere long both parties took up armes, ſo as no man could ſafely travaile on the high-way becauſe of the Souldiers, ver. 25. the event of this warre was this; firſt, the people were ruined, ver. 44. the City deſtroyed and ſowne with ſalt, ver. 45. the Tower, a ſtrong hold of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem,</hi> burnt, and a thouſand men and women in it, ver. 49. and ere long, the King was ruined, and that diſhonourably, ver. 53, 54. a ſad and heavy caſe, to ſee a body tearing out its owne bowels, to ſee a Kingdome, like <hi>Judas</hi> or <hi>Achitophel,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it ſelfe away when the Lord ſends a ſpirit of perverſities amongſt a people, <hi>Iſa. 19. 14.</hi> (the Lord hath mingled a ſpirit of perverſities, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it's a ſad thing when Courtiers and favourites of a King, who much mind not any Religion, yet come to Church and perhaps take a Proteſtation, the better to pleaſe men and keep their places a while, but as ſoon as they eſpie their time, take advantage upon a King, and labour to ſeduce &amp; draw his heart from God and his truth, to idolatry, and to raiſe up armes and make warre upon his Subjects, and this hath been done, ſee 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 23. 16. in <hi>Jehojada's</hi> dayes the Courtiers and people entred into Covenant to be the Lords people, and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed idolatry, ver. 17. but aſſoon as <hi>Jehojada</hi> was dead, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 24. 15. the flattering CGurtiers with their congies, obeyſance and cringes, vowing they would ſerve King <hi>Joaſh</hi> for ever, ver. 17. and eſpying their advantage with the King, wrought upon his nature, and drew him away with them from the pure wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, ver. 18. but ſee what warres followed, and what became of thoſe Courtiers, ver. 23.</p>
            <p>Yea, ſometimes a Queen, the wife of his boſome, may draw a King away, as <hi>Jezabel</hi> to <hi>Ahab,</hi> that was an high addition to all his other ſinnes, that he took <hi>Jezabel</hi> to wife, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 16. 31. and there was none like him, whom his wife <hi>Jezabel</hi> ſtirred up: <note n="b" place="margin">1 Kin. 21. 25</note> ſo <hi>Solomon's</hi> wives, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 3, 7, 8. and rending his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113511:8"/> Kingdome followed upon it, ver. 11, 13, 14, &amp;c. ſo <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. 2. 14. thus the Sonne of godly <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> did evill, becauſe led away by a bad wife, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 6. we read 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22. 1. that the <note n="c" place="margin">So the people met to make Rehoboam King 1 King. 12. 1. See Deut. 17. 14, 15, &amp;c.</note> people made <hi>Ahaziah</hi> King (called <hi>Jehoahaz,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21. 17 and <hi>Azariah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22. 6.) but two things drew him away, a bad mother, and her bad kinred and Counſellours, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 22. 3, 4. (if not a third, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. 27.) and theſe cauſe warres and diviſions.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it's a ſad thing when ſome young flattering Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers be neer about the King, that perſwade him to ſtand upon his points and prerogative, and not to condiſcend to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects petitions at all, but either to rule by his own will (an arbitrary government) or elſe venture his Kingdom and all; thus did <hi>Rehoboam's</hi> young Counſellours, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. <hi>Solomon</hi> was the wiſeſt of meer mortals, he had a thouſand Wives and Concubines, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11. 3. and yet had but one ſonne, and he fooliſh; when his Subjects came humbly petitioning his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtly, <hi>Rehoboam</hi> takes the advice of Malignant young Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, who tell him, would I have my neck under my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects girdles? either rule at your own will, and keep them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or adventure all, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11. and ſee what rents in the Kingdom followed, ver. 16.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it's a ſad thing when malignant Counſellours and paraſites about the King, who ſtudy the humours of Princes, lye at watch to ſpye an advantage, while they may take the King in a fit mood, to perſwade him to ruine the Church and people of God, yea, ſubtilly entrap the King, and get his hand and ſeal (or elſe ſigne it themſelves, and counterfeit his hand) to a decree deſtructive to the honeſt party, and by their deep plots draw the Kings heart away from them; thus did the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of <hi>Daniel</hi> ſubtilly work upon King <hi>Darius,</hi> and got a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree ſigned for <hi>Daniels</hi> ruine, though againſt the Kings mind, whoſe conſcience told him, that <hi>Daniel</hi> was a faithfuller and honeſter Subject then they, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 5, 6, 9. they pretend they ſtand for the Kings honour, and that this decree is only for the Kings greater glory, ver. 7. the King ere long ſaw himſelf abuſed by them, but could not mend it, ver. 14.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, it's a ſad thing when flatterers about the King per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113511:9"/> him that thoſe who are Gods beſt ſervants, and the Kings faithfulleſt Subjects, are Rebels and Traitors, and the Kings enemies; thus they accuſe Chriſt to be enemy to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and that he would hinder his tribute and revenues of the Crown, <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 2. and they that favoured him were no friends to <hi>Caeſar</hi> (that word ſtruck deep) <hi>John</hi> 19. 12. thus the three childrens enemies perſwade the King, that they are enemies and rebels againſt him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 12. ſo did <hi>Daniels</hi> enemies, <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 13. thus <hi>At halia</hi> cryes treaſon, treaſon, (but who was the Traitor?) ſo foul-mouthed <hi>Rabſbekah</hi> cryes rebellion, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 18. 20. thus Courtier <hi>Haman</hi> would preſwade King <hi>Ahaſuerus</hi> that the Jewes (Gods beſt ſervants, and the Kings beſt ſubjects, whereof one <hi>Mordecai</hi> had done more faithfull ſervice to the King, then an hundred flattering <hi>Hamans)</hi> were a factious, perverſe people, regarded not the King nor his lawes, and were againſt his profit, <hi>Ester</hi> 3. 8.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, it's a ſad thing when thoſe that are neer a King, not only whiſper and tell lyes and tales to draw his heart away from his beſt Subjects, but alſo uſe all means, yea adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture purſe and life and all to ruine ſuch: <hi>Balaam</hi> the Witch <hi>(Joſh.</hi> 13. 22. <hi>Numb.</hi> 24. 1.) would ſeek to Heaven and Hel to ruine Iſrael; Moabites and Midianites were content to make their daughters whores to ruine them; ſo deſperate is the old Serpents malice, (ſee <hi>Numb.</hi> 25. 1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 14.) thus <hi>Haman,</hi> who would never give a penny to a good cauſe (not only makes the King glad with his lyes, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 3. as before) but will give ten thouſand talents to the Churches ruine, <hi>Eſter</hi> 3. 8. ſo that curſed Edomite <hi>Doeg</hi> (a ſtranger, but now made a Courtier) not onely lyes againſt the honeſt party, and ſets on the King (who of himſelf was eager enough againſt them,) <hi>Pſal.</hi> 52. 3. but himſelf (when the reſt refuſed) playes the Butcher, not onely ſlaying the Prieſts (as he was bidden, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 18.) but alſo man, woman and child beyond his commiſſion, ver. 19 and ſo brings much crying guiltleſſe blood upon the King and his owne head.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, it's a ſad thing when Miniſters (that ſhould be men of God) adviſe and harten a King on to ſuch a warre as
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113511:9"/> a matter of conſcience; thus <hi>Zedekiah</hi> with four hundred Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, or rather ſatan by them, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 22. 21. perſwades <hi>Ahab</hi> to go up to a battle, which proved deſtructive to himſelf, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22. 11, 12. and how bitter was <hi>Zedekiah</hi> againſt the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ver. 24. (a godly Miniſter hath not a worſe enemy in the world, then a wicked, wretched Miniſter, ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 26. 8, 11. with ver. 16.) hence followed a war that ruined King <hi>Ahab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eighthly, it's a ſad thing when ſome bloody minded men even force a King (for their own ſafety, gain or ends) beyond his own inclination. Let me put a caſe; I can tell you of a King that had two Nephews, his own ſiſters ſons, the elder of theſe was General of the King his Uncle's Army, he was a furious, bloody-minded man, yet oft times the King his Uncle could not reſtrain him, but at laſt the King and he fell out, and the blood that he ſhed, fals in time upon his own head; my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, <hi>David</hi> the King had a ſiſter called <hi>Zerviah,</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 Chron. 2. 15, 16.</note> ſhe had two ſons, (for the third was dead, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 18, 23.) <hi>Joah</hi> the elder of these was <hi>David's</hi> (his Uncles) General of his Army, he was bloody, very bloody, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 5. yet his Uncle ſometimes could not rule him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 39. at laſt they fell out, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 5, 6. and his cruelty is revenged upon him, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2. 32, 34.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, it's a ſad thing when there is emulation and envy amongſt Commanders in Armyes, or betwixt chief perſons of the ſame ſide, ſo that out of envy ſome deſert the cauſe, leave off, or turn to the other ſide; how did <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Miriam</hi> envy <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 12. thus great General <hi>Abner</hi> makes <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> King, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 9. (as the great Earl of <hi>Warwick</hi> ſaid, it's more honour to make, then be a King) <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> afterwards reproves this Souldier for whoring, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 7. preſently <hi>Abner</hi> takes this in ſnuffe, and revolts to the other ſide, and loſeth <hi>Iſhbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi> his Kingdom, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 9, 10. ere long <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Abner</hi> (two great Commanders) envy one another, and <hi>Abner</hi> is ſlain ver. 27. ſee <hi>Achitophel</hi> and <hi>Huſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> claſhings.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, it's a ſad thing when Souldiers make but a play of war and killing men, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Let the men ariſe and play be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us:]</hi> and care not how long the wars laſt, or what ruine is done, ſo they may thrive, ſaying with <hi>Demetrius,</hi> by this craft we get our wealth, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 25. all theſe are ſad things,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113511:10"/> which are but the beginnings and occaſions of war: But the point will further appear, if we conſider war it ſelf, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ours, and that but in a word (for I at once conſider my time and your occaſions.) Therefore</p>
            <p>Secondly, view a little what a ſad thing war is; firſt, of all judgments war ſeems to be the ſoreſt, by <hi>David's</hi> choyce, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 14, &amp;c. ſecondly, of all wars civill wars <note n="e" place="margin">Graud. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ifice.</note> are wont nothing got but grating one upon another, like mil-ſtones without griſt (as I have ſhewed elſwhere <note n="f" place="margin">Summum (Brute) neſ as Civilia bella ſatenuer, Ceto. apud Claud. 1. 2.</note> in many particulars at large;) thirdly, of all civill wars, Engliſh war is <note n="g" place="margin">Bella pox Emitheos plus quam Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilia Campas. See Mark 3. 24, 25.</note> the worſt, ſee the Barons war compared with forraigne troubles; fourthly, of all Engliſh wars theſe preſent wars is worſt, if we conſider, firſt, the truell bloody minds of the adverſaries, who profeſſe they had rather the Turk or Devil prevailed, then the Round-heads; ſecondly, in former times of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity (as in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes) there was an <hi>Ireland</hi> to fly to, not now, then ſixty or ſeventy ſuffered, now ſo many thouſands, then lands deſcended to the Martyrs heirs, but if this Parliament be by force brought down, you may write upon the doors of your Liberties and eſtates, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> the conſequents of war (I will clean but a few) as, firſt, plague; ſecondly famine <note n="h" place="margin">Ier. 14, 3, 4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; 52. 6. Lam 4. 7, 10. &amp; 2. 20. 2 King. 6. 26, 30. 2 Sam. 24. 13, 15.</note> (read <hi>Jeremy</hi> and <hi>Joſephus</hi> for both theſe on <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> once and again;) thirdly, firing, <hi>Jer.</hi> 52. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3. <hi>Judg.</hi> 1. 8. &amp; 20. 48. &amp;c. fourthly, plundering, <note n="i" place="margin">Where is ſtrife there is every evil work, Iames 3. 16. Iſa. 13. 16.</note> many godly men left thouſleſſe, without Harbour, victuals, goods, money in an hour, by one party nor by another, what the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-worm leaves; the locuſt, ranker worm or caterpillar eats, <hi>Joel</hi> 1. 4. we whoſe goods eſcape the ſword of <hi>Hazael,</hi> yet plundered by <hi>Jebues,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Sabenns, Chaldeans,</hi> &amp;c. fifthly, want of means of grace, <note n="k" place="margin">Amos 8. 11, 12.</note> neglect of ſtudies, Paſtors dare not come at their Flock, but hide themſelves, <hi>Jor.</hi> 36. 26. nor Flocks at the Congregation; the wayes to <hi>Sion</hi> mourn, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 7. ſixthly, want of execution of good <note n="l" place="margin">Iudg. 5. 11. &amp; 17. 6. Lam. 2. 9. Inter Arma ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent leges.</note> laws, where all things are lawfull, nothing is right; ſeventhly, want of chriſtian ſociety of Saints, who are ſcatteved, perhaps never meet together again, husband and wife, parents and children in this world, <hi>Acts 8. 1. Math.</hi> 2. 14. eighthly, want of tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113511:10"/> none dare paſſe the high-wayes, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5. 6. <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. 22. <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. 18. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33. 8. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 5. ninthly, many like <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth,</hi> lamed, wounded, want arms, legs, &amp;c. tenthly, many (whoſe blood is precious in Gods ſight) are ſlain, and their blood run down the ſtreet, part from their friends, and never returne againe, <hi>Acts</hi> 12. 2. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35. 23, 24. <hi>Judg.</hi> 20. <note place="margin">Iſa. 3. 5. Lam. 4. 5. &amp; 5. 8.</note> 21, 25, 35, &amp;c. and many of the beggarly and baſer ſort, ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle houſes, and domineer over the perſons of ſuch worthies, whom they durſt heretofore ſcarce look at.</p>
            <p>But I have much work yet to do, and little time, I adjourn the reaſons; the truth of the point is apparent, and I accoaſt upon an Uſe or two.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 1. <hi>Ad Magistratum,</hi> all you that be in places of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and power, uſe all lawfull means, doe what in you lyes for the ſheathing up of the ſword, the preventing plunderings, ſpoilings, &amp;c. and removing theſe ſad calamities, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Ad Clerum</hi> (as we uſe the phraſe) pray we, and preach, and uſe our beſt endeavours for the compoſing of theſe differences, preventing theſe ſpoilings and robbings, to our griefe we ſee it; the Papiſts take away the ſecond Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Courtiers did take away the fourth Commadement, Plunderers the eighth, and the abuſe of theſe wars in many places the pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ice of all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Ad Populum,</hi> and that in divers things; and firſt, be we all affected with mourning ſpirits for theſe ſad judgments, war, and the fruits of it, as were <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah. Nehemiab, Jeremiah, &amp;c. Jer. 4. 19. Ezek. 21. 9, 10. My bowels, my bowels, &amp;c. Should we now make mirth? &amp;c.]</hi> take we up the lamentation, <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 48, 49. 51. <hi>Look away from me, I will weep bitterly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. 4. conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering firſt, what a land we lately had, like the Garden of God before theſe wars, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 3. ſecondly, how wofully now ſpoil'd eſpecially in many places, like a deſolate Wilderneſſe, <hi>ibid.</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 5. no peace to him that goes out or comes in: Thirdly, by whom all this is, <hi>viz.</hi> one neighbour againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea, and by Papiſts (and their confederates) who in quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times burnt living men, women and children, and digged others out of the grave to burn their dead bodies; what would they now doe? Fourthly, how long it may yet laſt, <note n="m" place="margin">The firſt Carthaginian war lasted 23 yeers, that betwixt the Hollanders and Spain about 70 yeers,</note> we ſee the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113511:11"/> differences are greatned, miſeries hightned, and gape, widened every day, diviſions in Church grow greater, and diviſions in the State not leſſer; ſee alſo how long the calamities were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Iſrael in <hi>Aegipt,</hi> upon the Jews in <hi>Babylon,</hi> upon <hi>Germany</hi> of late yeers, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, pray hard for thoſe of our Brethren, that be in, and under the ſury of battle, and the cruelty of the enemies; and that firſt, they may not ſin, that they may keep a good conſcience; alas, this is their hour of temptation and ſore tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, Satan is winnowing them, pray their faith may not fail, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 31, 32. ſee our caſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. 26, 31. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62. 6, 7. pray God to keep them from ſinning, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 20, 21. <hi>Jer.</hi> 14. 19, 21. Secondly, pray God to ſanctifie theſe troubles to them, to take away the ſcum, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24. 6. to fan away the chaffe, purge away the droſſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27. 9. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 2, 3. Thirdly, in due and the fitteſt time to deliver them from their troubles, and recompence the enemy, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79. 11, 12.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, endeavour in thy place and calling, to ſtench theſe wars, this bleeding wound, by firſt, repenting towards God: ſecondly, not willingly aſſiſting the Enemies of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, ſo as to hinder Delinquents from juſtice, or in what we are able any other juſt way.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Prepare for the worſt, who knowes what ſad dayes we may yet ſee, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. 15, 16. eſpecially if we ſeriouſly look at, firſt, our ſins and abuſe of great mercies; ſecondly, what far better men then we have ſuffered before us; thirdly, how many clouds and mountains ſeem yet to be betwixt us and a quiet end; fourthly, how ſins in every part of the Land yet encreaſe; fifthly, how all Treaties and probable means of reconciliation ſtill knap aſunder; we thought if ever the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies met, one battle would do it, but, &amp;c. ſixthly, what ſelfiſhneſſe and ends are yet in men, what envy and emulation, that ſometimes we cannot agree to follow the probableſt means cloſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore prepare (I ſay) for the worſt that can come, and truſt not, firſt, to policy (how little hath been done in theſe warres, by the deepeſt dungeon politicians (thoſe who were thought the wits and <hi>Achitophels</hi> of our time) even as much as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113511:11"/> 
               <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Achitophel</hi> did; God hath befooled men, I <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 19.) ſecondly, nor to riches, oft-times they make men fare the worſt, as at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> 
               <note n="o" place="margin">2 King. 25. 9, 12.</note> and maſſacre at <hi>Paris;</hi> thirdly, nor to ſtrong wals &amp; works (as was ſaid to <hi>Phocas) Nahum</hi> 3. 12. fourthly, nor to multitude of ſouldiers, ſtrength of men and horſe: But firſt, turn to him that ſmiteth ſpeedily, cordially, throughly, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 12, 14. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6. 1. Secondly, get into the Ark, <hi>Noah's</hi> Cabbin, Jeſus Chriſt by faith; then ſafe, if floods come, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 20. thirdly, take heed of lying in any ſin ſecurely, <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 7. fourthly, look to uprightneſſe, that fundamentall grace of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, pluck up a good heart; ſo <hi>Hezekiah, Iſa.</hi> 38. 3. fifthly, keep peace with Heaven and conſcience, however things goe here below; ſixthly, gang loof off from the creature, take heed of being inſnared now, <hi>Jer.</hi> 45. 5. Seventhly, hide thy treaſure in Heaven, where no plundering, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2. Reproves thoſe that delight in war, and are the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked incendiaries of theſe troubles, and ſtill adde (for their own ends) fuell to the fire, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68. 30. And this delight is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, either, Firſt, by cuſtome in the wars; about five or ſix yeers agoe, what a ſtrange thing was it to hear of a man ſlain, or eſpecially if twenty or thirty ſlain, now (to many once fleſht in it) but a play, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 14, 15, 16. or ſecondly, tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery; ſhould two Neighbours have walked together ſeven yeers agoe, and one of them ſhould have wept; his friend asks him, why weepeſt thou? the other ſhould anſwer, I fore-ſee within theſe four or five yeers the Papiſts and Atheiſts in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> will raiſe a horrid rebellion; and I foreſee, that though thou and I walk to Church together, eat and drink together, yet thou wilt join in the ſame cauſe with them, and wilt plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my houſe, ſeek to betray me and mine, yea, to ſlay me, &amp;c. this would have been thought ſtrange, yet now proved true in many; ſee this 'twixt <hi>Eliſha</hi> and <hi>Hazael,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 11. how true is that now in many, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55. 12, 13, 14. God hath opened a window in mens breſts (as ſometimes through the wall to <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in a viſion, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. 8.) whereby their hollow-hearted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath been diſcovered: Thirdly, gaine, as <hi>Demetrius</hi> ſaid, <hi>By this craft they get their wealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But if ſword and war be ſuch ſore judgements, <hi>Ezek.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:113511:12"/> 14. 21. is not war then ſimply unlawfull? <hi>Anſw.</hi> ſo ſaid <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>Lactantius</hi> of old, ſo <hi>Eraſmus</hi> and others of late, others affirm it unlawfull only to Chriſtians in the new Teſtament (as Anabaptiſts formerly) but he that conſiders that war is an art, firſt, of Gods teaching, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. 34. &amp; 144. 1. ſecondly, of Gods directing, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 2. thirdly, commanding, Numb. 31. 1. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 6. 2. himſelf Captain, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5. 14. fourthly, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by choyſeſt Saints, with good approof from God, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban, Joſhua, Gideon, David, &amp;c.</hi> Secondly, ye war with men profeſſing the ſame true Religion with you is lawfull, <hi>Jndg.</hi> 20. 28, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 13. &amp; 18. 7. yea thirdly, in new Teſtament lawfull, as appears, firſt, by Chriſts direction, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 14. and ſecondly, the Magiſtrates Commiſſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14. and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the Saints practice allowed, as Centuriou, &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 8. 10. <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 1, 2, 4. <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. 14. he needs not doubt the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 2. But ſecondly, the greater Quere is, When, and in what caſes war is lawfull? <hi>An.</hi> firſt, in generall (for we ſpeak of ordinary war) when it's neceſſary, and when no other means can obtain our juſt and neceſſary deſires; but in particular, our Caſuiſts require four conditions to a juſt and lawfull was: Firſt, lawfull and ſufficient authority requiring it; ſecondly, a juſt cauſe; and not only ſo, but weighty (not <hi>de l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na capitan)</hi> but firſt, for defending of our laws, lives, liberties, &amp;c. as a <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 1. &amp; 18. 7. ſecondly, for taking juſt revenge upon ſuch as doe publike wrong, out-face juſtice, Malignancs, Delinquents &amp;c. <hi>Jud.</hi> 20. 8, 18. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 2. 2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. 10. 7. or 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> toregain ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unjuſtly taken or detained by Land or Sea, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 14. &amp;c. 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 13. 5. Thirdly, a right end, not to maintain a popiſh <hi>Diana,</hi> nor any faction, or private opinion, not inrolled in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred writ (ſuch as of which <hi>Chryſippus</hi> uſed to ſay, that many times he wanted new opinions to broach, but if he had the opinion, he never wanted arguments to defend it) not to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine monopolies, great places, to get other mens eſtates, to revenge private ſpleen, &amp;c. but to obtain a juſt peace, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 2. ſo 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 2. it's there ſaid, that <hi>David</hi> demanded of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> how the war proſpered; in the Hebrew it is [of the peace of the war] <hi>i. e.</hi> in what readineſſe the war was for a peaceable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113511:12"/> end; the end of ſuits is to be quiet; and of phyſick is health: Fourthly, a right manner of managing the war for ſuch an end; as, firſt, undertaking it by prayer in the fear of God, <hi>Judg.</hi> 20. ſecondly, when we goe along in a juſt manner, not to phanſie a man guilty for a word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. 31. or for praying <hi>Dan.</hi> 6. 5. thereby to plunder him, not to accuſe men falſly, but be content with their wages, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 14. not to whore, be drunk, ſteal, &amp;c. holineſſe ſhould be on the bels of the horſes, and ſouldiers blades, as well as Prieſts frontlet, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14. 20. <hi>Deut.</hi> 23. 9, 14. thirdly, firſttender tearms of peace, <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. 10, 11, 12. fourthly, carry it wiſely, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>Deut.</hi> 20. 38.</p>
            <p>There is yet a third Quere, more difficult then the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and that is;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> 3. What may be ſaid for the lawfulneſſe of theſe wars which the Parliament now maintain; are not thoſe againſt the King, and ſo unlawfull?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I have elſwhere ſaid my thoughts, <note n="p" place="margin">Brittains Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> at preſent take this; firſt, that there ſhould be Rulers, or ſuperiours over men, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23. 3. is <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> all lawfull government, whether Monarchy, Ariſtocracy, Democracy; whether Kings, or (which were before them in Iſrael, Judges, Patriarchs; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Conſuls, Dictators, Tribunes, &amp;c. in a word, all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full government is of God, and the Ordinance of God, this is cleer by the light of nature, reaſon, Scripture, old Teſtament and new: But ſecondly, whether this or that Kingdom (or any particular Nation now) ſhall be governed by Kings, States or Conſuls, by a Monarchicall, Ariſtocraticall, or Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall government, this can be but <hi>Jure Humano,</hi> according as that people at their firſt union, coalition and fundamentall conſtitution, did bargain or agree; God never by his Word or Revelation ſaid, that <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould be governed by Kings any more then <hi>Holland, Venice, &amp;c.</hi> when <hi>Rome</hi> was governed by Conſuls, Dictators, &amp;c. it was lawfull, according as they did agree for the publike good and ſafety of the State; the world hath yet not ſtood ſix thouſand yeers, and the greater part of this time that the world hath ſtood was ſpent, ere Gods Iſrael had a King, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 5, 6, 7. yea, among the Jewes, where they needed no Parliaments (for God him.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113511:13"/> ſelf made and gave them their Law of the Land) and God had a ſpeciall hand in choice of their Kings (more then can be ſaid of any Kings now) yet even then the people had a hand and conſent in the choice of their Kings, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 14, 15. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 22. 1. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12. 1, &amp;c. much more in any other Kingdoms) the inſtitution of government is of God; but the conſtitution of this or that particular government, is from men.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if any Nation be governed by Kings, yet what line or family ſhall be the Kings or chiefe governours there, this is from man, or according as the people firſt made their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact, gave their binding conſent and choice: Marriage is Gods Ordinance, but whether this woman ſhall have this man to be her head, is by her own choice and conſent; God hath not ſaid, thou ſuch a one, be thou King of <hi>Spain,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, ſuppoſe this line or family, King of this or that Nation, yet whether he ſhall be King for yeers, or for life, or to him and his heirs, or to him and his heirs males for ever, this is <hi>Jure humane,</hi> a humane Ordinance, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as that Nation firſt made their bargain, agreement, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, what priviledges, Prerogatives ſuch a King ſhall have, what liberties immunities that people under him ſhall have, this is <hi>Jure humano,</hi> according as they have, and do make the bargaine, according to the fundamentall conſtitutions, agreements and laws of that Land (for <hi>France, Spain, Denmark, Hungary,</hi> &amp;c. are not all bound by any word of God to have juſt the ſame liberties, laws, prerogatives, &amp;c. but according as themſelves agree, ſo they be not againſt the generall rules in Scripture; ſo that I herein concur with the Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> that our caſe is not ſo much to be reſolved by Divinity, but law; and properly to be determined by thoſe who are Judges of what is, or is not law; what are, or are not the fundamentall conſtitutions of our government: Now to the caſe in <hi>England,</hi> the King was never made or eſteemed Judge of Law; men uſed not to goe to the King to know what is Law; &amp; if he ſaid this or that to be Law, it was but his own opinion; neither are our Lawyers or inferiour Courts the ultimate Judges, but the laſt Judge from which there is no appeal with us, is the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Court of Parliament: (now no Court of the Kingdom
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113511:13"/> is null, or the acts of it void, becauſe the Kings perſon is not there, or his mind againſt it.) This ſupream Judicatory affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and declaring to me, that by the fundamentall conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conſtant agreements and laws of this land, we may defend our laws, liberties, lives, eſtates, &amp;c. by arms, and that now is this caſe, and neceſſity thereof; I beleeve it, and have no further to goe for reſolution in this caſe: The objection of conqueſt is fond and frivolous; an unjuſt conqueſt without juſt title (meerly becauſe another is ſtronger) gives a man no right to my purſe, without my conſent ſome way, much leſſe to a Kingdome; ſhould the Turk or Spaniard unjuſtly make wars upon our King <hi>Charles,</hi> and conquer him, have they a juſt right therefore to his Kingdom?</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, I conceive a man may very much ſee the hand of God in theſe wars going along with the Parliament; if we conſider, firſt, the beginning of them, and that firſt, when we were very low, when by reaſon of flatterers, &amp;c. many were baniſhed and terrified, ſo as it was thought no man durſt lift up his head, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1. 21. yet thouſands appeared preſently; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, when it was thought that by idleneſſe and long diſuſe we were grown ſo effeminate, ruſty and unfit for war, yet have we found men not bred, but made as gallant ſouldiers on the ſudden, as any in the world; thirdly, when we were embroiled in a war with our brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet ſome of both Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons delivered, like brands out of the fire, for this work, <hi>Zach.</hi> 3. 2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if we conſider the growth of them, firſt, God hath wrought upon mens ſpirits, and that is above mans work, <hi>Haggai</hi> 1. 14. God touched mens hearts, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. 1. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 26. and hath fitted men like <hi>Bezaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab, Exod.</hi> 31. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their naturall temper for this work; of weak, made ſtrong; of dull, made quick, ſee <hi>Judg.</hi> 6. 1, 6. a ſtrong, potent enemy, ver. 5. yet a poor Leader (a thraſher) <hi>Gideon,</hi> mean perſon, mean family, mean furniture, weapons, &amp;c. pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider how God hath befooled the ſtrongeſt wits and ſubtilleſt, deepeſt plots in this buſineſſe, how little mens deepe plots have done in this work, but God hath car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113511:14"/> on-things beyond the wit of man, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 19. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44. 29. had thoſe reaching wits many a time taken a quite contrary courſe, how much in probability, had we been endangered?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we have gone moſt forward by going backward, gained moſt by our loſſes, like that plot, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 8. 20. 22. at our loſſe of <hi>Albertan, Bristol, Leicoster,</hi> &amp;c. how did our ſeeming friends turn, and were diſcovered, and when we were weakeſt, we did moſt; in moſt great victories, we almoſt quite loſt all, ere we conquered, as <hi>Keinton, Newbery, Heſſam-More, Naſeby,</hi> &amp;c. at <hi>Atherton</hi> we firſt won, then loſt all.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, our enemies have helped and furthered us much in this work; how came the Biſhops to be ſhut out of the Houſe of Lords, Delinquents from the Houſe of Commons, but by their own deeds? trecherous perſons and plots diſcovered the enemies victories and plots knit the Houſes firmlier together when any breach, and won them a peg higher (ſee <hi>Daniels</hi> three childrens, and <hi>Joſephs</hi> enemies raiſed them, this is <hi>Digi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Dei.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, Religions purity, the plots and filth of popery more diſcovered; tell me of any war in all the world (Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Romans, &amp;c.) that ever looked at the power and purity of Religion ſo much as this:</p>
            <p>Seventhly, the work is done, not by might or by power, but Gods way, by Gods ſpirit, <hi>Zech.</hi> 4. 6. like <hi>Jericho's</hi> waſe, the way that <hi>Babybon</hi> muſt down, <hi>Revel.</hi> 14. 6, 7, 8. and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt fall, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 8. <hi>Ezra</hi> 5. 1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But Antichriſt ſeems to befar from his fall and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Conſider if as great things, and as unlikely have not been done in <hi>England</hi> within theſe few yeers, he that ſhould have told thee but ſix yeers agoe, that we ſhould have an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble Parliament (ſave by its own power) that it ſhould
<note place="margin">The Lord is gone out beſore us, Iudg. 4. 14.</note> laſt above five yeers together, that there ſhould be never a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoly or Biſhop in <hi>England,</hi> that the Book of Common-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and twenty ſuch things ſhould be removed; would you have beleeved them? may not we ſay, God hath done wonders that we looked not for, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64. 3. <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi> 15. 11. and who knowes but God may ſay, thou ſhalt ſee greater things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113511:14"/> 
               <hi>John</hi> 5. 20. then may we change our praiſes as they, <hi>Jer.</hi> 16. 14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when Antichriſt goes down, he will goe down ſuddenly, like his Maſter, <hi>Luke</hi> 10. 17. like <hi>Pharaoh, Human, Belſhazzar,</hi> unexpectedly, ſee <hi>Revel.</hi> 18. 8, 10, 17, 19, 21. like a great mil-ſtone thrown down violently.</p>
            <p>Eightly, God hath done much already, he hath already made that good to us in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 2. that Gods people take them captives, whoſe captives they were, and rule over their oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: but the time warns me, let this ſerve for the firſt point, and I will diſpatch the reſt in few, or elſe prorogue them. The next is,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſerv. </seg>3</label> That when wars, plunderings, &amp;c. befall a Nation, it's God that ſends them, that gives up a people to them, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 24. 3. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 5, 6. <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 3. the enemies are Gods rod, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10. 5. Gods ſword, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 13. Gods battle-Axe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. 20. And this is not without reaſon, if we look at Gods glory, on his peoples benefit: <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> Firſt, at Gods glory; he hereby manifeſts wiſdome, in diſcovering the cowardly, trecherous and rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, the plots of open enemies, and falſhoods of ſeeming friends, are in times of wars and plunderings much diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, many ſuch viſions like that <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. 8. hath God revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his power; that he can make medicines of poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, bring light out of darkneſſe, and much good to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Church by wars and loſſes, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 9. and in the firſt time (eft times as worſt, as <hi>Iſaac)</hi> deliver them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. make devouring Whales and Lyons help and ſave them, as <hi>Jonah, Daniel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, his love; when the wars and ſpoilers have left them nothing but a God to live upon, yet oft times then have they moſt enlarged, full comfort, as <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Patmos,</hi> &amp;c. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Acts 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. In regard of his people, God ſuffers plunderers; and that, Firſt, hereby to put them in mind of their former abuſe of their houſes, lands, eſtates and liberties, therefore ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers them to be plundered of them, and to teach them to prize and value them better another time, and God in them.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113511:15"/>
            <p>Secondly, to prevent ſome ſpirituall diſeaſe, or ſore evil that he ſees would elſe grow upon them, perhaps pride, carnal ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, looſneſſe, therefore he hedgeth their way with theſe thornes, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 7.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, to quicken them to duties with more heat, to cry more heartily, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 5. 15. to take away their ſcum, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 24. 6. to make them ſhine brighter, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. 34, 35. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4. 3, 4. <hi>Zech.</hi> 13. 8, 9. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 25, 26. &amp; 27. 9. and other ſuch good ends, which I have formerly mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. To apply it briefly, firſt, art thou robbed, plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſpoiled, look up higher then man, as <hi>Job</hi> did, <hi>Job</hi> 1. 21. &amp; 2. 10. as <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39. 9. not like dog at the ſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. Snarl not, but learn patience, it is God hath done it, who is juſt and wiſe, who may doe what he will, who will doe what is beſt; it's a fathers cup and rod; any thing on this ſide hel is mercy; thou art no poorer yet, then thou came in, and muſt goe out of the world: Conſider firſt, ſuch a ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting patient frame of heart God loves and likes, and looks for, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 26. ſecondly, ſuch a frame of ſpirit hath a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of eaſe and delivery, <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. 41, 42. thirdly, with ſuch ſubmiſſion caſt thy care on God, and thou needeſt take no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracting care in the worſt times, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 5, 6, 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Is it God? here is a cordial in the worſt times; he can take off theſe ſpoilers, plunderers again (who ſent them) when he will; go to him, he can hook back a <hi>Zenacherib,</hi> bring down a <hi>Pharaoh, Herod, Haman,</hi> when he pleaſeth, by Angels, Stars, winds, rains above; by Lyons, Whales, lice, frogs, &amp;c. below; weak means, contrary means, no means, <hi>Job</hi> 34. 20. when paſt hope in mans eye, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. 36, as <hi>Iſaac, Jonab,</hi> &amp;c. wait on God then in theſe hardeſt times, and comfort we our ſelves: for firſt, are there not a great number of <hi>Abels</hi> ſlain, whoſe blood cries under the Altar, <hi>Revel.</hi> 6. 9, 10. and will not God avenge his elect ſpeedily? <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 7, 8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 51. 35.</p>
            <p>Secondly, many Saints (though dead) have left prayers for theſe times, and for this work, who ſowed what others muſt reap, <hi>John</hi> 4. and laid the firſt ſtone of this work, and theſe prayers are upon the fyle.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:113511:15"/>
            <p>Thirdly, there are many thouſand Saints alive, for whom God will doe much, as for ten righteous in <hi>Sodom,</hi> for the wheats ſake, yea, many young ones comming on (and we uſe not to execute a woman while great. with child;) the Lord often bleſſeth a <hi>Potiphar,</hi> a <hi>Labans</hi> houſe, for a <hi>Joſeph,</hi> a <hi>Jacob's</hi> ſake; when the great men of a Kingdom be in a combuſtion, yet the Saints then are the ſtrength of a Land, <hi>Zech.</hi> 12. 5, 6.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we have a thouſand of wraſtling prayers goe to God daily for this cauſe, if one poor widow can ſo prevail with an unjuſt Judge, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. one <hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 32. 26. how much more the Armies of prayers that begirt Heaven; the thing that we aime at, that Chriſt may raign, is the deſire of the godly in all Nations, <hi>Haggai</hi> 2. 6, 7.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, we have many ſweet experiments, taſtes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of what we deſire already; the buſh is not conſumed, two Kingdomes reconciled, much done already, many grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous yoaks we are freed from.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, Gods Name is much engaged in this work, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 12. <hi>Numb.</hi> 14. 15, 16.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, enemies ſins ripen apace, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 16. <hi>Zech.</hi> 5. 9. <hi>Ephah</hi> fils apace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. Learn to profit under Gods rod; and that firſt, by ſeeking our wayes more then formerly, <hi>Haggai</hi> 1. 7. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 40. (you hear my haſte;) ſecondly, accept the puniſhment meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Micah</hi> 7. 9. <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. 41. thirdly, learn obedience, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 10. &amp; 5. 8. fourthly, learn reformation, <hi>Joſh. 7. Iſa.</hi> 9. 13, 14. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6. 1. fiftly, prize mercies more hereafter, and uſe them better. For firſt, this is Gods end when he ſends theſe robbers and troubles, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3. 5, 7. ſecondly, it was the Churches way, <hi>Davids Pſal.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26. 9. thirdly, then the plaſter will fall off, &amp;c. But to end it:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 5. Laſtly, art thou, thy friends, or Church diſtreſſed, look up at him for cure that made the wound, meet God, <hi>Amos</hi> 4. 12. ſeek his face, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7. 13, 14. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 80. 3. yea, cry to God for help now; for firſt, the enemies are very cruel, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 83. 3, 4. ſecondly, Church in much need, like a woman in travail, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to bring forth an excellent birth, but a Dragon ſtands rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to devour it, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. many are like thoſe wicked ſpirits,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113511:16"/> 
               <hi>Mark</hi> 9. when they ſee they muſt be caſt out, they rend all (though a Kingdom) in pieces; thirdly, God expects thy cries for his ſick Spouſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 37. fourthly, Church expects and cals for it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 51. 18. <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 1, 2, 17. But may I but have leave to give you a brief of what I ſhould have ſaid to the other points, and I have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 3. <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſins and iniquities are the procuring and meritorious cauſes of <hi>Jacobs</hi> puniſhment, <hi>Micah</hi> 6. 9. <hi>Jer,</hi> 9. 12. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 4. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. 1, 2. and no wonder; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> firſt, it's but juſt that God ſhould ſend plunderers and ſpoilers to rob us; when we by ſin doe what in us lyes to plunder God of his Sabhaths, of his pure worſhip, of his praiſe, of his obedience, of his goods, our ſouls and body: Secondly, ſin gives God the lye; it is ſo ſaith God; it's not, ſaith ſin; let me have my will, ſaith God; nay, but I will have my will, ſaith the ſinner: There is no peace to the wicked, ſaith God; I ſhall have peace, though I walk in the imagination of my own heart, ſaith the ſinner: Such and ſuch perſons cannot be ſaved, ſaith God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 10. oh but they ſhall, ſaith the ſinner: thirdly, ſin would take away Gods ſoveraignty; a wicked wretch could with there was no God, and will not have Chriſt to rule over him: fourthly, ſin croſſeth the nature of God; he is not only holy, but holineſſe; not onely righteous, but righteouſneſſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 23. 6. but ſin is unrighteouſneſſe, it's a very oppoſition to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite truth and juſtice, &amp;c. fiftly, ſin kicks God upon the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, abuſeth infinite kindneſſe, patience; for which of my good works doe you ſtone me? wherein have I wearied you, &amp;c. no wonder then if this procure ſore puniſhments: A word or two of Application ſhall ſhut up this point.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. See then whom to blame for all the miſeries that have and ſtill doe befall us; all the Nations in the world could not have put us into that condition that our ſins have, and that juſtly; we but drink as we brewed; cleer God in all, he hath done nothing without a cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. It informs as alſo, who is the greateſt Malignant in all <hi>England, Scotland, Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> truly ſin; there are bad Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, but ſin is worſe, elſe all hel could not have made us thus miſerable and diſtracted.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113511:16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. Let this ſhew us ſin in a right glaſſe, and hereby learn to hate and leave it; we may ſay of this war as <hi>Zipporah</hi> of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> a bloody war haſt thou been unto me, in which ſome have loſt their husbands, ſome their ſons, ſome their friends, ſome their eſtates; but then chiefly ſay, oh bloody ſins that cauſed all this: There are four glaſſes wherein I would ſhew you the baſeneſſe of ſin: Firſt, in the riſe and ſpring of it, it's a baſtard, whereof the Devil is the father &amp; mans naughty heart the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; who would nurſe ſuch a brat, &amp;c. Secondly, in the nature of it, it's a thwarting and croſſing God and his law to his face: Thirdly,
<note n="q" place="margin">See two clean Birds.</note> by way of compariſon, dirt, poyſon, croſſes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, hell, are nothing ſo ill as ſinne, but ſhadowes of it, &amp;c. fourthly, in the effects of it; ſee what miſery it brought upon Angels; Secondly, <hi>Adam;</hi> thirdly, <hi>Sodom;</hi> fourthly; old world; fiftly, what troubles on Jeſus Chriſt: ſixtly, on all the world to this day, it's a make-bate and break-peace every where, in Heaven, earth and hel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 4. Exhorts us as ever we would have war removed, ſword ſheathed, wounds healed, break off our ſins by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; would you like it to ſee your Town robbed and ſpoiled, your channels run with blood, your houſes plundered? if not, forſake your ſins that procure theſe; then firſt, acknowledge <note place="margin">1 Iohn 1. 9. Hoſ. 5. 15.</note> thy ſinne, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 5. and thy worthineſſe to periſh forthy ſin, come before the Lord like <hi>Benhadad,</hi> with ropes about your necks, ſay, Lord if thou wilt condemne me, here I am, thou ſhalt need no other witneſſe; acknowledge thy ſins, national, perſonal, inſide and out-ſide.</p>
            <p>Secondly, break off thy darling ſin, that is a main work, this faſting day, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58. it's not conſeſſing, like <hi>Judas,</hi> or ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloath with <hi>Ahab,</hi> will ſerve without this, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. 11, 15.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, doe the contrary good, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. 29. repenting was expreſſed in the ſonnes doing the contrary to his former finnes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, mourn, lend a tear to a poor ſick mother when we are almoſt robbed of our God of our King, of our Religion, and our liberties, of our eſtates, of our friends and lives, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtill in many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the growing hand; ſhould we now make, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 1. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21. 6. be not inſenſible; but a word of this in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113511:17"/> the next point, and an end. Which is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 4. That when God pours theſe ſore calamities of war, ſpoiling, &amp;c. aforementioned, upon a people, he expects they ſhould be ſenſible of, affected with them and mourn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and is very angry and diſpleaſed, if they doe not lay them to heart; and no wonder, for firſt, God cals for this mourning temper, when he afflicts a people, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. 12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 15, 16. ſecondly, Church cals for it, have pitty upon me, have pitty upon me, <hi>Job</hi> 19. 21. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2. 18, 19. thirdly, God complains when we are not affected with the rod, when we lay it not to heart, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7. 9. <hi>Amos</hi> 6. 6. <hi>Obad. v,</hi> 12, 13. ſo doth the Church alſo complain for want thereof, <hi>Lam.</hi> 1. 12. fourthly, the Saints of God have laid Gods rod ſore to heart, when it hath layen on their brethren, though themſelves have been free; thus <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> though he had proviſion, wine, &amp;c. enough, and was ſervant in ordinary to the higheſt Potentate on earth, <hi>Neh.</hi> 1. 3, 4. &amp; 2. 2, 3. ſo <hi>Daniel</hi> one of the higheſt ſubjects on earth. ſee how he is affected with the Churches ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities, <hi>Dan.</hi> 10. 3. ſo <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 1. witneſſe his Lamentations, ſee <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. 11. ſee <hi>Eliſha,</hi> when he but foreſaw the miſeries that would come on Iſrael, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 11, 12. above all, ſee Chriſt over <hi>Jeruſalem, Luke</hi> 19. 41, 41. And reaſon good, if we look at, firſt, God; ſecondly, our Brethren that ſuffer, or thirdly, our ſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. In regard of God, it's he that ſtrikes, his rod, his work, his ſtrange work, and ſhould we not be affected then? if a father laſh one child, ſmite another, chide a third, ſhall not the reſt lay it to heart; a child of God trembles at his word, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. 2. much more at his blows and judgments; the Church trembled and were all afraid, when but one or two were ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 11. how much more when God ſtrikes down thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, <hi>David</hi> cryes, he was afraid of Gods judgements, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 120.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in regard of God alſo, becauſe in plundering, fighting, robbing times, there is much wickedneſſe committed againſt God; ſee in our times what open wickedneſſe againſt both Law and Goſpel; what profeſſed Atheiſme againſt the firſt Commandement, like him that was adviſed to leave ſin,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113511:17"/> elſe there was hel for him, cried, <hi>Tune credam cum illuc venero;</hi> or that Souldier that on the one side of his ſhield (as he fancied) pictured the image of God, with theſe words under it, <hi>Si tu non vis,</hi> on the other ſide, the Devil, and under it theſe words, <hi>Isle rogitat,</hi> if God will not, the Devil will; that was all that he cared: So what open Idolatry againſt the ſecond Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement (Atheiſts and Papiſts being combined together,) what prophane ſwearing, curſing, damming, ramming, banning againſt the third; ſo that many men (tolerably civill ſeven yeers agoe) cannot now ſpeak except they ſwear; I think veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God hath given them over to that in wrath; which they at firſt prided themſelves in; for the fourth Commandement, we need no books of ſports to be read to cry it down; amongſt many, it's almoſt forgot, ſome denying it in opinion, others in practice; for the fifth, how doe the vileſt people if ſtronger, inſult over the ancient, rifle his houſe, ſo that he whoſe face they durſt ſcarce (the other day) look at, cannot ſay, his houſe, lands, goods, wife, children, &amp;c. are his own, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3. 5. <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. 5. &amp; 5. 8. but drag him forth of his houſe bare, though gray headed and bare-foot, and uſe him villanouſly, as <hi>Phocas</hi> did to that good Emperour <hi>Mauritius,</hi> for murder, whordome and ſtealing, (breaches of the ſixth, ſeventh and eighth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements) which uſually goe together; how rarely are theſe puniſhed? nay, made but a jeſt? plundering, ſmoaking, &amp;c. lying is grown a trade in word, writing, print, &amp;c. For the Goſpel, how do men jeer at it, the goſpellers, goſpel lives, faith, &amp;c. nay, how do ſome openly caſt off the old Teſtament &amp; much of the new, both in doctrine and practice? and ſhould we not, nay, can we but lay theſe things to heart that are practiſed in theſe plundering times? if our father, husband, wife, &amp;c. vvas ſtruck down, vve would mourn; and is not God dearer to us then a thouſand friends, ſhall vve not lay it to heart vvhen men grow vvorſe then Devils, <hi>James</hi> 2. 19. neither beleeve nor tremble?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, vvhen the enemy gets a petty victory, Gods name is blaſphemed, therefore ſhould vve be affected and afflicted, he cannot be content to ſtrip, plunder, beat the poor Saint (whom he blaſphemes Round-head) but he muſt rail on and revile his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113511:18"/> God; where is your God now? what is become of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, Conventicles, long prayers, praying by the ſpirit? alas, this kils a <hi>Davids</hi> heart, troubles old <hi>Eli</hi> and his daughter, more then other croſſes, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 18, 19, 21. Pſal. 74. 18, 19. &amp; 79. 10, 11. ſo <hi>Moſes, Exod. 32. 11. Numb. 14. 16.</hi> ſo Pſal. 3. 2. &amp; 10. 13. &amp; 42. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. In regard of our Brethren and Country; for firſt, many are baniſhed, plundered, wounded, ſlain, their houſes burned, themſelves outwardly undone, that are very dear to God, whoſe lives are precious, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. 2. blood precious, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 14. death precious, Pſal. 116. 15. Gods ſervants, friends, children, heirs, Chriſts fellows (fellow ſervants, fellow ſufferers fellow conquerors, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. fellow judges, 1 <hi>Cor,</hi> 6. 2. fellow citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 17. nay, Chriſts ſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, partakers of divine promiſes, divine nature, divine (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municable) priviledges of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4. and ſhall we not lay this to heart?</p>
            <p>Secondly, they are neer to us, of the ſame houſe with us (for all Gods Church is but one houſe, only ſeverall Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Parlours, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 17.) nay, members of ſame body, under ſame head, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 12, 26. and when theſe ſuffer deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhall not we mourn? then are we but glaſſie eyes, and wooden legs, no living members; ſhall Chriſt be ſenſible, who is the head, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 4, 5. <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. 42, 43. and not your fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members? 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 29. 1. <hi>John</hi> 2. 9, 10.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, in regard of our Country; can we ſee our native Country ſpoiled, torn in pieces by its own ſons and not mourn? ſee <hi>Neh.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. 34. <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 3. how hath this dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſoyl and Kingdom been haraſſed and over-run by the Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (Anno 447. after Chriſt) whom King <hi>Vortiger</hi> ſent for to help him againſt the Picts and Scots, who came over hither under the conduct of <hi>Hengistus</hi> and <hi>Horſus,</hi> with about 9000. men at firſt, but after they had conquered the enemy, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered King <hi>Vortiger</hi> himſelf, ſlew his Nobles, got firſt a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in <hi>Kent (Thong Castle)</hi> then a County, then moſt part of our Kingdome, and made ſeven Kingdoms of it, plundered, baniſhed and ſpoiled the Brittains: After came in the Danes, fetcht in by one of our Nobility, <hi>Beorne Bockard</hi> (as ſome ſay, by occaſion of one <hi>Lothbroke)</hi> under the conduct of two Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Captains, <hi>Hunga</hi> and <hi>Hubba,</hi> upon the Danes comming in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113511:18"/> 
               <hi>England,</hi> they ſlew <hi>Osbert</hi> King of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> and ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged the cauſe of <hi>Bockard,</hi> &amp; after ſhot King <hi>Edmond</hi> to death with arrows, having bound him to a Tree, therein revenging the death of one <hi>Lothbroke</hi> (ſlain by one <hi>Beric</hi> King <hi>Edmonds</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coner:) Theſe Danes again plundered the poor Inhabitants of this Land, kept them under as ſlaves, ſo as they could not drink, but a Dane would cut an Engliſh-mans throat; hence were they fain to get one to pledge them when they drank, to ſave their throats from being cut. After this, came in the Normans from <hi>Normandy</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in the dayes of King <hi>Harold</hi> brought hither by <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> (after called <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> the Conquerer) landed neer <hi>Hastings</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> September 28. 1066. Duke <hi>William</hi> ſunk all his ſhips, that ſo his men might reſolve to fight (for fly they could not) fought with <hi>Harold</hi> October 14. in the yeer of Chriſt 1066. in which battle were ſlain about 68000. men, <hi>William</hi> proved the Conquerer, got the Crown, the poor Inhabitants were again plundered, their lands, places, eſtates were given to the French, many fled to <hi>Scotland,</hi> to King <hi>Malcolme</hi> there, &amp;c. but yet theſe were plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derings from forraign Nations, but now are we tearing out our own bowels in civil wars and broils one with another; it's true alſo, we have had terrible civill warres in <hi>England</hi> before this in the Barons war, in the diviſions twixt the houſes of <hi>Lancaster</hi> and <hi>York;</hi> but ſtill ours are worſe; when thoſe wars were at hotteſt, it's Chronicled for a ſtrange wonder, that in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, there were nine ſeverall bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels fought in that civil war, and yet he reigned (I think) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 23. yeers. But I can tell you of nine battles in half a yeer in King <hi>Charles</hi> his time, nay three times nine battles in three yeers of his Reign, and the Lord knows how many more yet may be. In every one of our late Soveraigns Reigns, there hath been ſome remarkable trouble or danger to this Laud; burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes, a Spaniſh Navy in 88 in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> days; a helliſh Powder-plot in 1605. in King <hi>Iames</hi> his days, but theſe troubles in King <hi>Charles</hi> his days exceed all the reſt; in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days ſome three hundred were burnt, in our days above thrice three thouſand ſlain; alas; how is our Country (lately like the Garden of God) now become a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113511:19"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:113511:19"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:113511:20"/> Wilderneſſe, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 3. that Land that <hi>Gregory</hi> (after cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the great) at <hi>Rome</hi> called Angel-land, a Land of Angels; which <hi>Spain</hi> called the fortunate Iſland; how ſits ſhe like a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow? <hi>alas,</hi> one comes from the Army and brings news like his 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4. 17. there hath been a great ſlaughter, and thy ſons are ſlain, and then what pitty to ſee how <hi>Rachel</hi> weeps becauſe they are not; another cries, my Husband is ſlaine; another comes like <hi>Jobs</hi> meſſengers, and cries, thy goods are plunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſheep and Cattel &amp;c. gone by the Sabeans, &amp;c. <hi>Job</hi> 1. another is ſhot to death, but lockt in the ſaddle, ſwags up and down; another hath his arme off, leg off, noſe off, hand off, &amp;c. ah, alas ten thouſand pitties! Corn-fields burnt, houſes; Churches burnt down, <hi>Iſa. 64. 10, 11. Pſal. 74. 4, 7.</hi> thumbs and toes cut off, as in <hi>Adonibezek's</hi> time, <hi>Judg.</hi> 1. 7. ſwords make women childleſſe, as in <hi>Agag's</hi> time, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 33. cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty uſed to living, yea and to the dead alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 79. 2. which a very <hi>Tacitus</hi> would have abhorred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. In regard of our ſelves: Firſt, our ſins have had as deep a ſhare in bringing theſe judgments as any, and ſhall we not be affected then with them? then are we worſe then the old Prophet was, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 13. 30. he hurt the young Prophet, but then mourned; <hi>Davids</hi> ſins hurt the people, Actions the Army; the peoples ſin hurt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah, 1 Chron.</hi> 13. 10. a bad ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack hurts a good head, and ſhall we not mourn then, as <hi>Daniel</hi> did in the like caſe? <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 5, 6.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe that which lies on others to day, may be our caſe to morrow, <hi>ille bodiè ego cras,</hi> as <hi>Bernards</hi> good old man ſaid, the cup may paſſe unto us, <hi>Lam.</hi> 4. 21. we may be forced to drink round of Gods cup, <hi>Jer.</hi> 25. 28, 29. &amp; 49. 12. ſay not they are greater ſinners then we that are ſharplier chaſtized, <hi>Luke</hi> 13. 4, 5. but lay it to heart as if we were in bonds, Heb. 13. 3. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 1. But I muſt break up; an Uſe or two therefore ſhortly, and I have done.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Of reproof to many (herein nigh a kin 20 <hi>Jacob,</hi> to Iſrael) that though we are thus given to the robbers and ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, yet conſider not, yet lay it not to heart; theſe are of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſorts; Firſt, they that are glad of it; en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>es cry, down with us, down to the ground, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137. 7. ſeeming friends,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113511:20"/> that ſay, hereby they get their wealth, <hi>Acts</hi> 19. 25. Newters of <hi>Gallio's</hi> temper, or of theirs, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Obadiah</hi> ver. 12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 35. 15.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they that are ſenſible of <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute them to a wrong cauſe, they ſay as Barbarians of <hi>Paul,</hi> or <hi>Job's</hi> friends of him, <hi>Surely Iacobs cauſe is naught, be goes in a wrong way, elſe had never been ſo given up to the ſpoilers and robbers; but oh ſee ere thou judge,</hi> Judg. 20. 21, 25.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they who are ſenſible of, and affected with the croſſe and trouble, not the ſin.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they that make it appear they are not affected with our miſeries and ſins, no not upon our humiliation, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and mourning dayes; for firſt, ſome come not, cannot ſpare time from work; ſecondly, other game, card, ſport this day, which is much more needleſſe then work; thirdly, others feaſt this day purpoſely, ſet up an anti-faſt, as well as an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parliament, ſee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. 12, 13, 14.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, others take occaſion this day, while you are ſhut up here mourning and weeping, and praying, to haunt Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and whordome, and pour more oaths out, and more cups in, then we pour out tears, like brazen-faced <hi>Zimri,</hi> when all the Congregation was weeping, <hi>Num.</hi> 25. 6.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, they that come hither and ſit here, but are not affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, mourn not; faſting days ſhould be weeping days, faſting and weeping uſed to be joyned together, <hi>Neh.</hi> 1. 4. <hi>Eſt.</hi> 43. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. 6. <hi>Joel</hi> 2. 12. many are very eager and earneſt in buying, in ſelling, trading, hunting, courſing, only mighty careleſſe, mindleſſe, in hearing, praying, and when they ſhould be weeping.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, others weep &amp; mourn for a day, but hold not out, are not like wraſtling <hi>Jacob,</hi> or the importunate widow, or like mourning <hi>Jeremy, Lam.</hi> 3. 50. till God look down and heal his Church: Now this inſenſibleneſse in theſe ſad days, this not laying theſe things to heart, is, firſt, a walking contrary to God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. 12. <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. 40. ſecondly, it argues much folly and blindneſſe of mind, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. 3, 4. thirdly, much hardneſſe of heart, worſe then <hi>Pharaoh, Manaſſes,</hi> Prodigall, they in times of croſſes relented, <hi>Exod.</hi> 9. 27, 28. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 33. 12. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113511:21"/> fourthly, it's a deſpiſing God; let him ſmite and doe what he will, ſaith the ſinner, I will not yeeld, like <hi>Balaam,</hi> will not turn back for all ſword and miracle, <hi>Numb.</hi> 22. fiftly, it argues a mervailous love of ſin, as the child that is whipping for playing with rattles, will ſtill play with them while he is on the knee whipping, ſure he loves them dearly, as <hi>Balaam</hi> did the wages of unrighteouſneſſe, ſo as word and ſword could not turn him, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 15. ſixtly, it argues want of love to Chriſt, 1 <hi>John.</hi> 3. 17. &amp; 4. 20. ſeventhly, want of love and zeal to Gods Cauſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. 18, 19. &amp; 79. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2. The ſecond Uſe ſhould have been for tryall, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are rightly affected with <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles; firſt, are we as much affected with them now, as we were at the beginning of theſe wars? ſecondly, how are we afflicted on dayes of humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Levit.</hi> 23. 27. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7. 16. thirdly, are we affected with ſin, the cauſe of all theſe troubles? fourthly, doe we turn from our evil vvays and reform, <hi>Jonah</hi> 3. 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. But to end, laſtly, be exhorted this mourning day, to conſider and lay to heart <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles; as firſt, the ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered dry bones of <hi>Germany;</hi> ſecondly, the <hi>Acheldema</hi> and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of <hi>Ireland;</hi> thirdly, the diviſions of <hi>Scotland;</hi> fourthly, the plunderings in <hi>England:</hi> fiftly, the fury of battle and ſword, hacking &amp; hewing amongſt us; ſixtly, the deſtroying Angel, the noyſome peſtilence in many places of our Land and Country; ſeventhly, the ſciſms, rents, old, new errours in the Church; eightly the encreaſe of ſin daily, of all kinds, as light encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth; there vvas light and knovvledge in King <hi>Edward</hi> the fixt his dayes, more in Queen <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> more ſtill in King <hi>James</hi> his, moſt in King <hi>Charles</hi> his dayes, yet ſtill ſin encreaſeth, yet ſome doe not ſee, ſome vvill not ſee, ſome pretend to ſee that vvhich is not to be ſeen; ninthly, God dravvs neerer and neerer vvith his judgements and vvarnings, begins novv to make his approaches, intrench and make his batteries; he began in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> came on to <hi>Ireland,</hi> then to <hi>Scotland,</hi> then to <hi>England,</hi> then to <hi>Yorkeſhire,</hi> then to the gates of <hi>Hull;</hi> and that firſt, mildlier, vvhen the King came to the gates in <hi>April</hi> 1642. then ſharplier in the firſt ſiege, then more terribly in the ſecond ſiege, from vvhich you vvere delivered <hi>Octob.</hi> 11. 1643. bevvare the fourth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113511:21"/> time; novv God knocks at the gates vvith a fear of the plague the King called in <hi>Anno</hi> 1642. the King of Kings knocks novv in 1645. tenthly, the danger of continuing theſe troubles, till all be daſht in pieces, and many ſuch like evils.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> What ſhould vve do? <hi>Anſ.</hi> firſt, ponder ſadly, the lands miſeries, the particulars, the quantity, the quality of them, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. 1. ſecondly, ponder thy ovvn evil vvays, as ſadly, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4. 4. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36. 31. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 40. ſift thy ſelf for thy ſins (as the word is <hi>Zeph.</hi> 2. 12.) when God ſifts the Land, <hi>Amos</hi> 9. 9. doe as the Prodigall, return to thy ſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 15. 17. thirdly, clear God in all this, and condemn thyſelf, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. 13. though thou art no rebel againſt the King, yet againſt the Kings King thou haſt been; fourthly, have a fellow feeling of thy brethrens miſeries <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 3. ſo as to pitty them in thy heart, <hi>Jer.</hi> 4. 19, 20. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3. 51. and pray for them with thy heart and tongue, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62. 3. help them in thy life, mourn for them, <hi>Neh.</hi> 1. 4. and look not only on them, as Prieſt and Levite did, but to thy power be a good Samaritan; thirdly, you that have power, puniſh wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and vice, let it not be now when the Kingdom bleeds (as a godly Divine ſaith) as hard to pull down a baſe Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Maſt.</hi> Bol.</note> as to win <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Motives might be many, but I will only hint at one or two and conclude: Firſt, to lay to heart <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, with the cauſe thereof, is the way to ſave us in time of danger, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. 4. when King <hi>Zedekiah</hi> would juggle on all ſides, mourning <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſpeaks home and plain, yet finds more favour from the Chaldeans heathen Army, then <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and all the Nobles, <hi>Jer.</hi> 39. 6, 7, 11, 12. ſo <hi>Eſter</hi> 4. 14. Secondly, we have ſet apart this day to lay to heart <hi>Jacobs</hi> troubles, let us doe the work that we came for: Thirdly, conſider how Jeſus Chriſt was and is affected with the churches miſeries, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 41. <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 4, 5. Fourthly, how great things now lye at ſtake, not an Army only new moulding, but Kingdom, &amp;c. but I to caſe you, and myſelf, break off with the ſad complaint of mourning <hi>Jeremy</hi> Lam. 3. 48, 49, 50, 51. <hi>Mine eye runneth down with rivers of water for the destruction of the daughter of my people; mine eye trickleth down and ceaſeth not, without any intermiſſion, till the Lord look down and behold from Heaven; mine eye affecteth my heart, becauſe of all the daughters of my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Decem. 26. 1645.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Impri.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOSEPH CARYL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
